<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of John Durie, a minister of Jesus Christ to witness the gospell of peace wherein he doth make known the truth of his way and comportment in all these times of trouble : and how he hath endeavoured to follow peace and righteousness therein innocently towards all : that the offences taken against him, through the mis-construction of some, of his actions may be removed : and the work of peace and unity amongst the Protestant churches at home and abroad advanced in due time.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37063</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13245062</idno>
  <idno type="VID">98655</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240907260</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8208</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13245062</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98655)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of John Durie, a minister of Jesus Christ to witness the gospell of peace wherein he doth make known the truth of his way and comportment in all these times of trouble : and how he hath endeavoured to follow peace and righteousness therein innocently towards all : that the offences taken against him, through the mis-construction of some, of his actions may be removed : and the work of peace and unity amongst the Protestant churches at home and abroad advanced in due time.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98655:1"/>
            <p>A Declaration OF JOHN DURIE, A Minister of Jesus Christ to witness the Gospell of Peace.</p>
            <p>Wherein he doth make known the Truth of his way and comportment in all these times of trouble;</p>
            <p>And how he hath endeavoured to follow Peace and Righteousness therein innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards all:</p>
            <p>That the offences taken against him, through the mis-construction of some, of his actions may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; and the work of Peace and Unity amongst the Protestant Churches at home and abroad advanced in due time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98655:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98655:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration OF JOHN DURIE, A Minister of Jesus Christ to witness the Gospell of Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing there is a heavy woe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced against those by whom offences come;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.7.</note> therefore it is a duty incumbent upon every one, to purge himselfe from the guilt thereof, either by an ingenious confession or a clear vindication of his innocency, if an offence be not given by him, but taken at him. And seeing I have been lately informed, in a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner by some of speciall credit, who have a particular dependance upon his Majesty, and know the sense of those that are about him; that amongst them there is a report whereunto cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit is given; that I have been very opposite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98655:3"/>his Majesties affairs and interests; and that having quitted the service of the Princes Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all at the <hi>Hague,</hi> I have been since subservient unto his Majesties enemies, in these and also in forraign parts; nay that I have approved of the proceedings of those that put his Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to death: all which being odious crimes, and the last being very atrocious: therefore I have thought it necessary by the manifestation of the truth to vindicate mine own innocency from such aspersions, and to secure my self and my reputation in the Churches of Christ from such prejudices and mis-informations, which obstruct the work of Peace, and have none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground but the mis-understanding and mis-construction of such actions, which (being out of the common road,<note place="margin">The motives for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of <hi>1.</hi> is Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> and free from private ends) have not been rightly discerned by such as have not so much aimed at the means of common edification, as at the furthering of a party. For which cause I am obliged to declare the naked truth of my comportment by a plain discovery of the Principles and of the Rules, of the Method and of the chief circumstances of my actions; as they have answered the design, whereunto by a solemn vow made unto God above twenty years ago, I was bound (and have consecrated my life) to serve Jesus Christ in the Gospell of Truth and Peace; namely <hi>That I should without all selfe ends or respect of Persons and Parties prosecute amongst the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, when and wheresoever God should give me ability and opportunity, the means of Peace
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98655:3"/>and Unity in the Truth, by the reconcilement of their differences and the removall of offences in a Gospell way Separate from all worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Declaration I conceive I am bound ro make at this time and upon this occasion, not onely lest my silence should confirm the evill report made of me to his Majesty, or lest I should seem to find my self guilty of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am accused; whereas in truth I am not to my self conscious of any guiltiness in that kind, <hi>(behold before God I lye not)</hi> but also lest the credit of my work amongst the Churches, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held for so many years, should now suffer under this reproach; as if it had been carried on for worldly ends to serve any mans turn; and lest the Gospel way wherein I have walked harmles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by provoking all different parties and chiefly their leaders in the Churches, to love and to good works towards each other; should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ineffectuall, and none should be stirred up any more by me, to tread this path, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Solicitor of the Counsells of Peace, when I shall have finished my course, for I am not ignorant of Satans devices by which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to blast and stop the progress of these proceedings, which now by his Majesties graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous countenance and Pious inclination may have a full and effectuall success; as being more then ever seasonable to be prosecuted for the preservation of the Protestant Cause and Religion; which in his letter to the House of Commons he hath owned with so much real and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98655:4"/>cordiall expressions, that every one who hath any sense of Piety or good will to the Church of God must needs heartily rejoyce thereat.</p>
            <p>To pay therefore this debt which I owe to the Truth, to the Churches of God, to the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of my Gospell design, work, and way, to mine own conscience, to my safety also as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now may stand; and to my reputation in after times; I shall declare in singlenes of heart: as in the presence of God the Truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matters which are laid unto my charge.</p>
            <p>And first concerning my going from the Court of the Princesse Royall; The main cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which moved me thereunto, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my removall thence, I hope will clear that action from any Sinister design.</p>
            <p>For after that I had been (without any the least thought of mine own) secretly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Sir <hi>William Boswell</hi> has Majesties Resident at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Dingly</hi> Secretary to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning my being at the Hague.</note> to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as Chaplain with the Princess Royall his Majesties daughter; I went to the <hi>Hague</hi> in obedience to his Majesties commands, and there I performed the duty of my place, in the family without blame carefully; till I found that the duties of attendance requisite at the Court, did eat up all my time, and so became severall ways inconsistent with the prosecution of my principall aim; wherein I had vowed to Dedicate my studies unto God, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of Gospell Peace and Unity in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98655:4"/>Churches. This gave me an inclination to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the course of my employment; but I did nothing to remove my selfe from it, till I reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Summons from the Parliament to come to the Assembly of Divines, which then sate at <hi>Westminster</hi> to give advice to them in Church matters: upon this call to assist in such a work; I confess I was coscionably moved to apply my self to the main scope of my studies; and that I might do it without offence, I wrote to the primat of Ardmagh, who then was with the King at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and intreated him to obtain leave from his Majesty for me to go to that As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly; hoping that I might be able to do his Majesty and the publick more profitable service there by helping to reconcile differences at home, then I could do at the <hi>Hague.</hi> This leave his Majesty gave me by a letter which Secretary <hi>Nicholas</hi> wrote unto Sir <hi>Wiliam Bos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from thence.</note> who acquainted me therewith in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties name; only I was desired first to go to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> Having gotten his Majesties permission; I did seek in like manner leave of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that I might go with his good liking thither, either by being wholly dismissed or for a time: but he was unwilling to grant that which I had obtained of his Majesty, therefore to remove the difficulty which he made to let me go, and which I made to stay; Doctor <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Sulichom</hi> his chief Secretary of State, were appointed to confer with me; and after severall meetings when nothing was agreed upon but delays made, another call was
<pb facs="tcp:98655:5"/>given me, to be Pastor of the English Church at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> which then wanted a Minister; I obtained leave to go thither upon a twofold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made by me to his Highness: 1. that I should stay so long with him, till he could find another Chaplain, who should bee able to supply my place, and whom the Dutch Ministers should not except against, but approve as they did me. Secondly, that I should help him to find out such a one. These things I promised to do: and when I had performed them, by bringing Mr. <hi>Harris</hi> Doctor <hi>Harris</hi> of <hi>Hanwell</hi> his Son from <hi>Utretch</hi> into my place; I went to <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> and the Prince gave me under his hand and seal a Testimony that I had his good leave to go away, and that I had behaved my selfe in the discharge of my place whilst I stayed with him dutifully and without offence.</p>
            <p>Being then come to <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> I found that by order from the Parliament the constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of that place was altered from that form, whereunto the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> had put it some time before; which occasioned a division amongst the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Society: I therefore intending to unite them in the substance of their Gospell-worship, followed a middle way, neither strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formall,<note place="margin">Concerning my being at Rotterdam.</note> nor altogether unformall; which did not offend the discreet and sober; but did not answer the expectation of the fiercer sort of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, who were neither fully displeased nor well pleased, with my moderation: and this I did advisedly as by my selfe without any pre-consultation
<pb facs="tcp:98655:5"/>with either party; to let them see that the true property of our Gospell-worship consists not in words &amp; formalities but in power: for I conceive that the worship of God in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Assemblies, may consist in set words and forms onely so far as these are subservient in an orderly way to beget and maintain in the soules of those that meet to worship God together; the power of Godliness by the unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.<note place="margin">And my cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry there by what rule it was order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Now by the power of Godliness I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the effectuall motions of the Spirit by which our souls drawing near unto God have communion with him: and the soul is said to draw neer unto God, when it hath a serious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and longing for the work of his grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it: and the motions of the Spirit beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and fomenting this desire are found to bee effectuall both in the Acts of our worship and in the course of our life and conversation. They are effectuall in our life by the works of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, of love and holiness; which God hath ordained that wee should walk therein that wee may have fellowship with him. <hi>For God doth meet him who joyfully worketh righteousness;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 64.5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16 <hi>Lev.</hi> 11.44 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.16.</note>
               <hi>and remembers him in his ways.</hi> And again it is said. <hi>He that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God; and God in him.</hi> And again it is said, <hi>be ye holy as I am holy,</hi> from whence the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> makes this inference; <hi>because he who calleth you is holy, therefore be ye holy in all manner of conversation.</hi> And this is to walk with God as <hi>Enoch</hi> did, whom at last God took to himselfe to an unseparable communion in heaven, herein
<pb facs="tcp:98655:6"/>doth the power of Godliness appear most effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and infallibly: Yet the motions of the Spirit are effectuall also in and by the Acts of worship, and that two ways, both within our own souls, and also outwardly towards others. Within our own souls both in the understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and in the will and affections; for when the understanding is helped thereby to conceive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and the heart by the will and affections is raised strongly to imbrace, the truth of the things wherewith the soul is Religiously conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant with God, in the Acts of devotion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Acts of praying to him, or of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of him, or of hearing his Word; then the motions of the Spirit are found to be effectul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and these same motions are also outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effectual towards others; when our behaviour in the Acts of worship is such, as becometh the beauty of Holiness &amp; fitted to edifie those with whom we joyn in those Acts: &amp; they are fitted to edifie others, when they appear to be serious &amp; devout; for then they work the same impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions upon the affections of others which they shew to be in our selves. The words then and the forms which are fittest to reach these endos, and to unite therein the Spirits, of those who are assembled to worship God together are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test to be used in a publick assembly; that is, the words and formes which are most intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible by all and proportioned to their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and answer the subject matter of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is to be performed most directly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affectation and superfluity (which seems
<pb facs="tcp:98655:6"/>to put the substance in words and repetitions) I say such words and formes I conceive are most answerable to the ends for which we meet together, to draw near unto God. And by this rule I made use of the Leiturgie at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> neither laying it wholly aside in respect of the substance of the prayers; nor binding my selfe strictly to the whole formality of it: and so I conceive, it may yet be made use of moffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively, according to the capacity of those that meet to edifie one another. Thus then I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till I was again called upon to come into <hi>England,</hi> to sit in the Assembly of Divines: where to prepare my way that I might sit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them without any scruple (because I knew that the Nationall Covenant would be offered unto me when I should come thither) I had already, whilst I was yet at the <hi>Hague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The manner how I went to the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Divines at Westminster</note> sent before hand in writing a Declaration, wherein I explained my sense of the Articles of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that it might be understood, that I would not otherwise be engaged to it, then as it was con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sistent with my former vows and promises made to advance the Gospell work, which I had nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated amongst the Churches and with the oath of Allegiance which I had taken to the King.</p>
            <p>This Declaration was read in the Assembly of Divines, and not contradicted by any; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as afterward I was told) some did grumble at the reading thereof, because they thought it did not become any to put his own sense and limitations upon the Covenant; and to publish that sense unto the Assembly: so then
<pb facs="tcp:98655:7"/>I went thither; not to foment one party against another, but to do my Gospell work, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to serve his Majesty for the Kingdoms wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare;<note place="margin">And my cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment there as to civil affairs</note> and this I did so as to keep an interest in all parties that I might do good offices between them. And when the personall Treaty was in agitation, because I conceived that it might tend to an agreement between the King and his Parliament I was forward to promote it; and that indeed was the onely Civill business wherein I thought fit to intermeddle, because most of all the other publick negotiations of State, had a tendency (so far as I could dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern) rather to widen, then to heal our brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And the true causes for which I did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly abstain from intermedling in State mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were chiefly these two. First because I perceived that when Ministers did intermeddle the heats were ordinarily rather increased then allayed. Secondly, because I was bound up by my vow, not to Act in State affairs otherwise, then as they should be subordinate or concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent with the end of my Spirituall employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I found not any who ruled in the State, willing to further my designe, without partiality, but onely for some interest whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I had no mind to become subsurvient.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved my self to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King when he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the High Court</note>But at last when the personall Treaty at the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> brought forth the sad and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected effect which increased our distractions, by the erecting of a high Court for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Tryall, then indeed, I made it a serious part of my work, first to prevent the Sentence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98655:7"/>&amp; secondly the execution of it; in the first to save his reputation, in the second his life. For I did conscionably judge my self bound to do for him, all which I could or should have done for mine own Father if he had been in his case: Therefore I went to one of the Masters of the Chancery, an able man, &amp; an intimate friend of mine; whom I found no lesse troubled at those proceedings then I was; to consult with him, what could be done for his Majesty to prevent the sentence which was apprehended to be given against him; whereupon he resolved to write down such argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as he conceived most effectual for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty to use at the High Court, in his own defence: of these arguments I gave one Copy to the Lady <hi>Vicountes Ranalaugh,</hi> who with my wife fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the Lady <hi>Monmouth</hi> therwith; that shee by Doctor <hi>Juxon</hi> his means might convey them to the King; and another Copy thereof I car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried my self to the Prince Elector <hi>Palatin,</hi> that when he should be permitted to go, to visit his Uncle he might give it unto him; which hee promised to do. This was to prevent the Sentence by a Legall plea: and then when the Sentence was pronounced; I sate up a whole night and wrote about two sheers of Paper, wherein I did plead against the execution of that sentence; by eight Classes of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which were inscribed and sent to the President and Judges of the High Court to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them to suspend it. These Arguments the Lady <hi>Ranalaugh</hi> aforesaid and my wife gave to Mistrisse <hi>Sutton,</hi> heretofore a School-Mistress
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98655:8"/>at <hi>Kensington,</hi> to be delivered by her to the President and Judges, and I am sure the President did receive them, for about a year and a half,<note place="margin">What I did to get the sentence su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spended.</note> or three quarters after that time; the President himself did shew mee that Paper and did ask me if I did know such a hand, whereunto I did answer affirmatively, and lookt him in the face stedfastly, whereupon he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded no further.</p>
            <p>Of this discourse (because I was in great hast to send it, at the time when the Court should sit) I could keep no Copy; yet the heads and substance thereof, I kept in a paper, and still have in my memory; and they were to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to shew</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it was neither lawfull for them of the High Court; nor expedient for the Nation; that their sentence should be put in execution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King:</hi> And that for these Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because the matter of debate between him and his Parliament was still as doubtfull as ever it was:<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulness &amp; unexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the tence.</note> namely which of them had first or most wronged each other, now for a Court, in a doubtfull Case, to proceed to the execution of a sentence, <hi>de facto, onely by power,</hi> is no way just or warrantable by any Laws of God or men.</p>
            <p n="2">2, Supposing the matter of debate to be out of all doubt between him and the first full As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embly of Parliament, namely that they and not he, were wronged; yet that the Deputies of a party onely should take upon them the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be Judges of the Kings person; without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98655:8"/>any known Law of the Nation; and without any example ever heard of in any Nations cannot be thought Just and Warrantable by any that is rationall; and therefore the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ought not to be executed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Supposing their Authority, to be Judges of matters of fact, to be unquestionable: yet by the undoubted Law of the Land, the Kings person is not punishable, but the Law takes hold only of his Instruments: therefore the execution of a Sentence against his person is not warrantable, although his actions might be Judged faulty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Supposing that there were no prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Law of the Land: yet by the Law of Nature and of Nations, it cannot be War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable that they who have no authority, nor right to make use of any power but from and by him, should use it to cut him off who gave it unto them. All that Nature will allow in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses extraordinary, as in Leprosie, or Madness, or in any other the like unfitness to Rule; is a restraint hindering him from doing hurt to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, therefore the execution of the Sentence against his Person is not Warrantable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Supposing this whole Plea, concerning the unlawfulness of executing the Sentence to be in respect of the Judges of the Court, worth nothing; yet the Plea of inexpediency in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Nation; will be many ways so considerable, that it will amount in respect of Conscience amongst Christians, to be equivalent unto that, which is unlawfull;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98655:9"/>because <hi>Salus Populi Suprema lex est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is no ways expedient for men of Conscience, but utterly unlawfull amongst Christians; to make it a crime worthy of death in any man to defend to the utmost of his power and according to the Custome of all Nations his undoubtedly supposed right; now the King having done on his part nothing, but to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with all his might the prerogatives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly supposed to belong unto him; as descended from his Ancestors and never here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore questioned: and the Commons, having on the other part upon the like ground of their supposed right; used the same means to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their priviledges; it is neither Warrantable in Conscience nor to such as pretend to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives of a Nation is it expedient; that they should execute a Sentence of death against him for doing that which all Kings have ever done; which all equals do one towards another; which they themselves on their part have done no less then he; and for the doing of which no man was ever yet blamed with reason.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But supposing (which no Conscionable man will deny) that there hath been faults on both sides; and supposing also that the Kings party hath been more faulty then the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which hath opposed him; yet in this case, it is extreamly unexpedient, if not altogether unlawfull to Christians and Conscionable men, to proceed against him without commiseration, and not to respect any humane frailties; So that he being misinformed and thereby being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98655:9"/>led out of the way by evill instruments, should not at all be found excusable; is the utmost ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of sevrtity; which becomes not Christian Subjects to use to their interiours; far less to their equalls, and least of all to their Rulers.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is most unsafe and unexpedient for the Nation; if not altogether unlawfull to Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and men of conscience; to make a quane I once begun to last for ever, and become al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether irreconcilable: it is unsafe every way both to those that have the power in their h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd now, and to the whole Nation, aswell in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of home bred divisions, as in respect of common enemies, who watch to destroy us: now the execution of this sentence will infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bring this to pass; as to men, except God work some miracle for us: therefore in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God; for the safety of the Nation, and for the preservation of themselves and of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir posterity, they ought to suspend the execution of this sentence.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Besides all these considerations the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of the Gospell, and our profession thereof, and the Protestant Cause will be ruined as to men by the execution of this sentence, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting reproach will be brought upon the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and upon the Protestant Religion thereby; not only amongst the enemies of the Truth who will insult and Triumph hereat, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst forraign Churches who will abhor and detest us and suffer persecution for our sake; all which will be a heavy guilt before God, upon those who execute the senteece; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98655:10"/>it ought to bee suspended.</p>
            <p>These were the summary heads of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, more at large discoursed upon and dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted warily, without passionate and provoking expressions, in a lamenting phrase and humble tone, for fear of giving offence; and with a Preface and conclusion shewing that these things were insinuated in a loving manner, to discharge a Conscionable duty towards the King; towards themselves also in compassion to their souls, towards the whole Nation, and towards our Religion to prevent the evills which might inevitably follow upon the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their sentence.</p>
            <p>But when this wrought nothing upon them, nor any other means used by other Ministers, nor the interposition of the <hi>Hollands</hi> Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors, could avail to stop their resolution; I went out of the Town, not to be in the place where so great a mischief was to be acted.</p>
            <p>This Act of violence did so highly provoke and inflame the Spirits of most of the Ministers, who were wont formerly in their Sermons to reflect much upon State matters of lesser con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments,<note place="margin">Wherefore I diswaded Ministers from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with State mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Pulpit.</note> that they see med to make it a main design, to incense the people to a trmultuous and inconsiderate rising; whereunto it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served that the Popish Emissaries also, and the chief of the Levellers, with whom they lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deck; (who always had opposed the Kings Interest) did concur at this time, to highten the animosities of the discontented parties to an utter confusion; which could not end, but in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98655:10"/>the totall ruine of that party which was yet affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Kings-Interest; if by their rash cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, they who had all the power of the State in their hand, and could not be resisted, should be provoked, or by tumults necessitated, to fall upon them. Therefore to obviat this danger, which was occasioned by the inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateness of some Ministers; I conceived it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the aim of my employment, and necessary to preserve the moderate party, to bear witness against that way and manner of preaching, which some followed by directing their setmons to meddle with the affairs of the State: to which effect I wrote a discourse, to shew that it did not belong to the Ministeriall work of the Gospell, to handle State matters in their sermons; or to inform the people concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the same as they were wont to do: This discourse displeased very many of the Brethren; and some were preparing to make it a Subject of dispute with me: which when I heard; I did enlarge the discourse as a Case of Conscience, to be soberly discussed, in a moderate and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar way to avoid vain jangling and offered the Gantlet to any that would enter the lists to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuss it with me either so as I proposed the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of disquirie; or any other way which wee might agree upon to come to a decision of our doubt: But no body did yet appear to enter with me upon that Subject in a debate: And whether it was any conviction upon the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of some; that their way was not sutable to their Gospell-work; or because they found
<pb facs="tcp:98655:11"/>that it could not do the cause any good at all, but only hurt themselves, and weaken, or disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the weakness of their party; by little and little that custome was left off.</p>
            <p>But when the <hi>Engagement</hi> was proposed to be taken, a greater difficulty did arise, in the Spirits of all that were moderate; and a more eminent danger was like to fall more fully, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Body of the Nation,<note place="margin">Wherefore and in what sense I held it lawfull to take the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</note> and chiefly upon that party in it, which did acknowledge the Kings just Right and Prerogative; and might in due time be a means to restore the same. For certainly it was the design of some, by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to oblige al by Pole, to exclude at least indirectly the King and Lords for ever from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a hand in the Government, by removing al that would not take the Engagement <hi>in terminis</hi> from having any safety &amp; protection in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Yet the words of the Engagement being so laid; that they could not inforce the sense <hi>w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>
               </hi> was aimed at, but could bear a clear sense, of a duty; w<hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">ch</seg>
               </hi> not being directly opposite to the Royal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, was advantagious to the welfare of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which two things should never be separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (though their aim was to separate them) I was moved to own the Engagement so far as I found it contained a clear duty; upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration whereof I thought it not only lawfull for me, but also sutable to the end of my design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed employment: to declare in what sense I took it to contain a Duty; namely as it obliged all to be true and faithfull to the Nation, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the absence of the King and of the House of Lords from the government. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98655:11"/>when I took the Engagement I gave my construction of it in writing to the President of the Council; as a Testimony that I took it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Nation with a <hi>Non obstante, and not otherwise.</hi> Which sense although they would not publickly own; yet I never heard any that durst deny it; nor was I refused to take it in that sense, and in my conscience I could not find it lawfull for me to refuse the taking of it so, if I should stay in the Nation to prosecute my design; seeing in that sense I did judge it to be a Duty consonant to all other Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments under which I had put my selfe; both in reference to my Gospell-work; and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Nationall Covenant; and to the oath of Allegiance.</p>
            <p>this then having been the ground, and the method of my proceeding in this matter; when the words of the Engagement came to be a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of debate amongst the Ministers (for few else did write in publick to scruple at it) I thought others might take it in the sense where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I had taken it; and that such as would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strite the meaning of it otherwise; as if it did oblige all, to oppose hereafter, the having of a King and House of Lords in the Nation, were in the wrong; and made a needless scruple to themselves and others; and gave those that sought thereby an advantage against them, an opportunity to put them out of place; and to disable them from doing good offices in due time: for seeing it was apparent enough that the Engagement was laid as a snare to entrap and sift such as were not fierce enough for their
<pb facs="tcp:98655:12"/>turn to go along with them: there was no reason wherefore any who could avoid the Snare with a good conscience should suffer himself to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by it, &amp; made useles for the publick; &amp; upon this account I did endeavour to quiet the scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Conscience which honest men had about the taking of the engagement; wherein I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived I did no disservice to the Truth; by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it in the best sense wherein it contained a clear Duty; and not in the worst, which it might bear, wherein it could not be owned; nor did I any disservice to the honest minded party by keeping them from a trap wherein they might be taken.</p>
            <p>But because in the disputes which arose about that subject, many matters were objected which did relate one way to the fundamentals of a State;<note place="margin">But I am not willing to defend all that hath been said by way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to qu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et scruples a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</note> another way to the fundamentals of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in respect of Christianity and Equity. And in State matters the constitution of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being reflected upon, sometimes as it is under the Law of Nature, sometimes as it is under positive Laws, and humane ordinances which are alterable; and the causes of the alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of laws &amp; of law making power, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered under several Notions, sometimes in <hi>Thesi,</hi> sometimes in <hi>Hypothesi:</hi> in all which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in the way of debating, many things have been uttered <hi>Argumentandi Causa,</hi> rather to quiet a scruple of Conscience, then to further any design whereby the right of any might be desined, limited or wronged: I say because such things, under such notions, were so disputed off, and by way of argument according to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb facs="tcp:98655:12"/>of the time raveled into, wherein many things may be unadvisedly uttered, and also construed otherwise then they were intended, by me; I will not stand to a stify them: for though I am no wayes comcious to my self of any declining from my former engagements and professed principle of Duty, which I have constantly to the best of my underst<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; yet seeing in many, not only words, but actions also, we are all subject to fail, either by doing too much or too little, or by varying in the manner of performance; therefore that the uprightness of my intentions, whereby I study to serve all in that which is most requisite, and that the usefulness of form<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r endeavors in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting those intentions towards all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, may not be bl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sted, for want of true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and self resignation, to the good and longed for Providence, whereby God hath mercifully turned all our changes to the best; I am not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing either to confess a failing herein; or to accept of the gracious favour and pardon which his Royal Ma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esty hath kindly offered in his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Declara ion to all,<note place="margin">I therefore take hold of the pardon <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffered by his Majesty.</note> that shall lay hold thereupon wi hin the time appointed, which by this Declaration thus made publick, I intend to do, aswell as to give satisfaction to all that are ingenuo s, and can construe either rationally or charitably the actions of a publick nature in Christianity, which are undertaken to heal the breaches of mens Spirits who are partial, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality.</p>
            <p>And because his Majesty doth not only grant
<pb facs="tcp:98655:13"/>a free and general pardon of all such failings, a either actu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly or interpretatively have been committed by any who returning to the Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd obedience of good subjects,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d offer my <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lt<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jesty in my Gospel work</note> are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted by the Parliament: I think my self bound to offer to his Majesty and this his Parliament, the disposal of the fruits of my thirty years ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation with all the Protestant Churches, for the advancement of their Peace and Unity; as it becometh a loyal and obedient subject to do; that they may be made use of, when it shall be seasonable for the publick good; in order to the fullfilling of that most pious and religious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, which his Majesty hath expressed in his Letter to the House of Commons; where he is pleased to say, <hi>That nothing can be proposed unto him to manifest his zeal and affection for the Protestant Religion, to which he will not readily consent.</hi> As then my whole course for so many years hath been directed to heal the breaches of Protestants amongst themselves, without which their Religion can never be propagated nor preserved; and in all that time, I never yet could sinda Patron to the work except <hi>S. T. Rowe,</hi> who for the love of the Truth, and out of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection to Religion without Politick self ends, would undertake the prmoting of it; so I must now in the fear of God take hold of this opportunity which God alone hath created by a most wonderful revolution of Providence; that if my services may be of use to his Churches, I may not <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eem defective in my willingnes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the fruits thereof unto the publick, rather
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98655:13"/>by his Majesties direction then under any of his predecessors, in the interval of Government.</p>
            <p>And to the end that this may appear unto such as are intelligent, and that the jealousy raised against me for my acting in this work under the Protector <hi>Oliver,</hi> as if I had been an instrument, sent abroad, and acted by him, to do his work towards forrain States; may be removed; I shall truly relate the motive, and the manner of my proceeding, to act my Gospel design under him.</p>
            <p>When he was made Protector, and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Peace was drawing towards a conclusion between <hi>England</hi> and the Low-Countries;<note place="margin">Concerning my acting under the Protector Oliver, that it was not for any of his designs.</note> and all that were in publick places did own him as the chief Magistrate of the Nations; I thought it sutable to the end for which I was come into <hi>England;</hi> and every way seasonable and fit for me to represent to him and to his Councel, some Reasons for which I conceived them obliged in conscience to mind the interest of Religion amongst Protestants, and to give some countenance to the endeavours whereby their differences might be reconciled. These Reasons were communicated also to the Ambassadors of the United Provinces while the Treaty was in agitation, who seemed much to approve of the design. The same reasons were also imparted unto the leading Ministers of the Congregation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Presbyterial Churches in <hi>London;</hi> who by my sollicitation were brought together, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occasion met several times for a special conference held at <hi>Black fryers</hi> to compose their
<pb facs="tcp:98655:14"/>own differences first, and so to joyne with me in the design of my negotiation towards the Churches: the chief heads of the Universities also, were made acquainted with the same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; which took this effect with them all, that they did approve of the work as very expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and seasonable to be undertaken: and to inable me to go about it, a Declaration was penned which the heads of both the Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and the Ministers of <hi>London,</hi> aswell Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational as Presbyterial did subscribe; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing me to Act that business amongst the Churches in their name: and when I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Commission and instructions from these, I desired nothing further from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector but his countenance and support; that he would only own me, as a Gospel Minister, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my self a part for the work of Peace and Unity almongst Protestants,<note place="margin">But only for my Gospel work.</note> I might have a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of recommendation from him to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Zwitzerland,</hi> in the Cantons of <hi>Zurich, Basel</hi> and <hi>Geneva;</hi> that they might know that I being approved by the chief of the Ministery of <hi>England</hi> for such a work, and moved of mine own accord to go about it, he could not refuse to recommend it unto them to be taken into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, promising also thereunto his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence; for I did of set purpose decline to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any commission in this business from him; or any instructions to act any thing for him in State affairs; because I neither would be, nor would I be lookt upon as an Agent of his going abroad to serve any of his ends: therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired
<pb facs="tcp:98655:14"/>(and that in writing as discreetly as I could) that if he had any State affairs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to forrainers, he would make use of some body else for that end: and although I knew that such a desire of mine would gain me little acceptance with him (as appeared in the end at my return) yet I resolved to keep my self free from such a Relation or subordination to him and his designs; lest my true aime, the liberty of my acting, and the nature of my work might suffer prejudice, and be justly blasted thereby when it should be found to have been made a cloak to his worldly advantages: and although I could almost no where at my first arrival into the places where I went to negotiate, avoid this kind of thought which both States men and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines would take up concerning me; yet before I went away, when they found nothing of that nature mixed with my Religious negotiation, nor my private discourses tending to insinuate any particular or personal advantages for him, to recommend him, further then what was in view to all the World: they found themselves alwayes mistaken in me; chiefly when some of them would propose unto me, things of that kind, and I would openly and professedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to meddle with them, telling them in plain terms that I neither was nor would be an Agent for the Protector in State or Policy concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>And although I could not be ignorant before I went abroad; and found it so effectually, when I was abroad; that this jealousy of State,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98655:15"/>with the <hi>odium</hi> and the danger accompanying it, would follow me every where; and chiefly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex my business with those that had any Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or affection to the Kings affairs, who would either avoid all dealing with me; or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>construe all that I should propose; by reason of the forestalement of their thoughts; that I was an emissary of his: and although I also did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present unto my self, that which I found after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be true; that my life might be in danger either by Papists in hatred to my work, or by them and others also in hatred to him, whom they would imagine I served; yet because I was assured that I served not man, but Christ; and was conversant in my calling lawfully, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently towards, all without any Politik designs; therefore I trusted unto God for Safeguard and Protection; and committed my wayes unto him, who also hath delivered me, and prospered me in my way and brought me home in fasety, for which I bless his Name.</p>
            <p>It was no difficult matter to conceive; that the whole aime which <hi>Oliver</hi> might have in countenancing me and my business; was to gaine some Reputation amongst the Protestant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be a Zelot for their Interest; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to wipe off the <hi>odium</hi> of his incroachment of power, as if it tended only to procure their well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: and truly this he did at first pretend with so much likelihood, that none but the searcher of hearts could certainly know it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; for although I could suspect at first some such thing might be possibly, yet I cannot say
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98655:15"/>that I could conclude it probably; but when I was come home, and had shewed how all things were laid for a Religious correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and prepared to carry on the work as it relates to the Gospell; then I could see plainly and demonstratively, that his aim was not that which at first he had pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; because when all was ready to his hand; and the Ministers here in <hi>England</hi> of different parties were disposed to act further in the work he did not at all mind the business further,<note place="margin">Which he deserted wholly at my return.</note> than by meer importunity of some honest Souldiers (which I got to sett upon him about it) hee was forced for shame, to recommend it to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther consideration of some Ministers, who met at <hi>White-Hall</hi> as Commissioners for the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of other Ministers: and this he did once superficially, desiring them to give him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward some account of their advice in the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but never would call upon them for it, nor countenance or favour me in prosecuting or solliciting of it: yet I have still proceeded in my way so far as God hath given me ability, and opportunity in these manifold and distracting changes; wherein notwithstanding all our sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings and movings, the foundation of a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous correspondency to prosecute the means of unity and Peace are laid and continued; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the endeavours may easily be renewed whensoever the Lord shall move those that are in authority to mind the things of Christ's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as the main end of their Government o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men: and not to make his Kingdom a cloak
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98655:16"/>and pretence to cover other ends and interest; of their own in the world; as hitherto most men whom I have met withall have done; or else have minded the Gospell-work onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functorily and in a Secondary place; and I am very confident: that because they have not sought the Kingdom of God and his Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness first and before all other things, therefore the other things which they have mainly sought, have not been added unto them: But when judgement shall return unto righteousness, then all that are upright in heart shall follow it: and upon such shall be peace, and upon the Israel of God; to whom I consecrate this and all my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavours as it becometh a witness and Solliciter of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98655:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>